[Music]
Hello and welcome to the session on
what's new in algo for GitHub telemetry
and dashboards. My name is Alexander
Hollstrop and I work as part of the
engineering system team at Microsoft and
one of my responsibilities is to be a
maintainer of the algo for GitHub
repository and that also means
contributing stuff like telemetry and
dashboards.
In this session today, I'll talk about
some of the latest improvements we made
around enabling a an easier starter
point for dashboards in a go for GitHub.
We already had a telemetry story before
that, but now we made it even easier to
get started with setting up your first
dashboard. Um the reason we've done this
is really that we've gotten feedback
that as the number of repositories grow
in your organization then it becomes
more difficult to get a full overview of
of all your DevOps processes and you
know whether there are build failures in
one repository out of a 100 it becomes
more difficult to get an overview of
this and that's where we believe
telemetry and dashboards can make all
the difference and it can it can really
help you get an overview of of all your
repositories in one place and so we
wanted to make that even easier than it
where he was uh by kind of giving you a
dashboard that you can use out of the
box and it should just work uh and
that's what I'll show you in this
session today. So to get started with
the dashboard, you first need to enable
telemetry for algo for GitHub. And uh
this is not a new feature, so I'll just
speedrun through it. But essentially
what you have to do is go into Azure and
set up an application insights resource.
Uh name it whatever you want, put in
your subscription.
Once it's created, then you'll see this
uh connection string in Azure portal
that you're going to need to copy.
And then you need to go into your algo
repository or your algo organization and
add an algo setting. And you know in
this case in this screenshot I'm I'm
showing as as a repository. But if you
have a lot of repositories it might make
sense to go into your organizational
settings and add uh this setting here.
Um the setting is called partner
telemetry connection string. And the
connection string is the one that you
copied from uh from the Azure portal. So
once you save this then you're
essentially already logging telemetry
for your AL go for GitHub repositories.
Uh so the next time your workflow runs
then you'll get telemetry for it in
application insights.
So that's really the first step. The the
next step here in the new thing is that
now we provide this start a dashboard
and in order to get started with that
you just need to go and download it from
uh from Algo's uh repository. uh you
need to change a few variables in there
and I'll show you how to do that and
then you can just upload it to Azure
data explorer and off you go. So I'll
show you how to do that in this uh short
little demo.
So the first thing you're going to do is
to go to akams/ale-go.
That'll take you to the algo repository
on GitHub. Um, in here you're going to
go under scenarios.
And under scenarios, you're going to
find a scenario called enabling link
telemetry. And I mean that that article
essentially has all the instructions for
how to get started with telemetry and
how to get started with this this new
dashboard. Uh, we've already gotten
started with telemetry. So I'll skip
past that and go down to the dashboard
section.
Uh, first step is you need to go and
download this file. If you open up this
code file in AS code, you'll see two
things that needs to be changed. You
need need to change the cluster URI and
the database. Uh and all of this is also
described in the article here. So the
database is really just the name of your
application insights resource in Azure
like my application insights or
whatever. Uh and the cluster URI has a
more like specific form to it that you
know I think the easiest way is just to
copy it from from the article and paste
it in here.
Uh so you fill in things like you know
my application insights
uh you need to fill in your resource
group and you need to fill in your
subscription ID and then down here you
just fill in uh the name of your
application insights resource. So my
application insights
you save this file and that's that's
really all you need to do. Um
the next step is you have to go to data
explorer.asure.com.
In here you can go to the dashboard
section
and if you go here and you click import
dashboard from file
you can create a dashboard.
And so now you have your first dashboard
up and running. It it takes a couple
minutes to do and then you know you have
you can see all the telemetry coming
from your repositories. Now in this case
I've been logging into telemetry for a
little while for four different
repositories and so you know I have some
data to look at. If you just set up
telemetry this will look fairly empty
for you but it'll it'll fill up as
telemetry starts coming in. Uh so in
this starter dashboard you can see the
number of repositories you're collecting
telemetry for the number of workflow
runs you can see the number of workflow
runs over time. Uh you can see the
failures over time. So, looks like here
on August 27th, we had a lot of
failures.
Um, if you scroll down further, you can
see a list of all the different workflow
runs and the failures. Uh, if you scroll
over, you also have the ability to go
straight to the GitHub UI.
So, you can see this workflow run here
that failed. Now, I can go into the
GitHub UI and investigate what happened,
why did it fail.
Uh, then we have another tab for
workflow duration. Uh this is really if
you want to monitor the the amount of
the total amount of time that it takes
for a particular workflow to run on
average in a particular repository. Uh
you can monitor that from here. Uh we
also have a graph down here that should
be loading. Uh where you'll be able to
see kind of a trend over time. So you
can monitor if uh you know if the
workflows suddenly start taking much
longer then you know that's something
for you to look into or create an issue
on it'll go to for us to look into. We
have another page here for runners. So
uh we know that a lot of partners are
using self-hosted runners and so if
you're one of them and you want to make
sure that everything that runs in your
algo for GitHub repositories runs on
self-hosted runners or vice versa um
this is something you can monitor for
this page. Uh so in our case we're
mostly using GitHub hosted runners but
you know it might look different for
you. Um you can also see the total
compute time in hours over time also
separated by GitHub hosted and
self-hosted.
Uh and finally we have some scenarios
where you can use Linux instead of
Windows. Uh in our case we're only using
Windows but down here you can also
monitor uh how many of those runner
minutes are running on Linux versus on
Windows.
And the final page we offer out of the
box is this uh ALGO maintenance page. Um
this is really for you to stay up to
date with you know what version of ALGO
that you're running in your repository
and whether that's the latest version of
ALGO that's available. Uh we have a link
here where you can always see what the
latest version of ALGO is if you click
on it. Uh right now as we're recording
this is version 7.3. So, I can see I
have a couple repositories here that I
need to update. Uh, and that's really
what this page is intended for is just,
you know, make sure that you're helping
you get up to date and stay up to date
with the latest versions of ALGO for
GitHub.
If you scroll down further, we can see
last time we ran the update algo system
files workflow. And finally, we have a
section on ALGO deprecations. So from
time to time we're going to deprecate
certain settings from algo. Uh typically
just because we replace it with another
setting instead. Uh and so when that
happens you'll get these warnings in
your in your dashboard and you can see
uh that you need to take action on these
things. And if you go to this article
here you can see exactly what you need
to do in order to to make sure that
these warnings uh go away. So that's
briefly uh what you can do with this
starter dashboard. U it helps you
monitor your workflows. You can monitor
build failures. Uh you can track build
duration and and so on. Uh so it has a
couple of those very, you know, simple
things that you can track. But of
course, this is only a starting point
and it's only meant to be a starting
point. You can take this dashboard and
you know go in your own direction and
start adding your own pages. Uh but if
you see something that you think this
could be useful for the whole ALGO
community, also feel free to contribute
it to the to the ALGO repository. Uh the
way you do that is to go to the ALGO
repository under discussions and then
ideas and just log an idea for some
improvement that you think both you
could benefit from but also the rest of
the ALGO community could benefit from.
Uh ALGO has always been open source and
so we we value these open source
contributions.
So in summary, the last latest version
of ALGO for GitHub now includes a
starter dashboard that makes it easier
than ever to get started with setting up
your first dashboard based on ALGO
telemetry. Uh all of the steps that I
just went through in this section here
is also covered in documentation. Uh
look for an article called enabling
telemetry and you'll find all the steps
that you need to take.
If you're looking for more resources,
you go to aka.ms/algo.
Uh if you go under discussions, you can
log an idea or a question. And finally,
we have an office hours call u the last
Tuesday of every month uh where you can
also ask your questions. So with that
thank you very much for watching the
session.